Guide to the John Emil Sepich Accessions
The Wittliff Collections
John Emil Sepich Accessions
1973-2007
The Wittliff Collections https://www.thewittliffcollections.txstate.edu
Sepich, John, 1951-
UPWC.05122
1 Linear Feet
20 folders
Multiple accessions from Cormac McCarthy scholar, John Emil Sepich, documenting McCarthy's work, notably Blood Meridian. Includes correspondence and writings from other other McCarthy scholars and translators.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research; however materials in Accession 2009-072 may not be photocopied or reproduced in any form without permission from the rights holders.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John Emil Sepich, 2005-2014
Biographical Note
John Emil Sepich is a historian and scholar of Cormac McCarthy. He is author of Notes on Blood Meridian.
Scope and Contents
Multiple accessions from Cormac McCarthy scholar, John Emil Sepich, documenting McCarthy's work, notably Blood Meridian. Includes correspondence and writings from other other McCarthy scholars and translators.
Index Terms
Subjects
American literature -- History and criticism; Literature -- Translations
Subjects (Persons)
McCarthy, Cormac, 1933-; Faria, Paulo
- Accession 2005-122
  Abstract
  One essay, "Knitting the Winds," by John Sepich.
  - Photocopy of typed essay titled "Knitting the Winds" by John Sepich, undated (Box 600)
- Accession 2005-164
  Two essays, "Why Believed the Judge?" and "Knitting the Winds," both by John Sepich.
  - Two typed essays titled Why Believe the Judge? and Knitting the Winds both by John Sepich, undated (Box 658)
  - Handwritten letter to Steve Davis from John Sepich, June 22, 2005 (Box 658)
- Accession 2006-033
  One booklet, "Notes on Blood Meridian," by John Sepich
  - Booklet, "Notes on Blood Meridian" by John Sepich, undated (Box 658)
- Accession 2006-144
  Collection of materials relating to John Sepich's study of Cormac McCarthy's novel, Blood Meridian, and other materials relating to Notes on Blood Meridian by Sepich. Items include: manuscripts, drafts, correspondence, research materials, notes, and copy of Sepich's thesis.
  - Typed clean short manuscript, pages 192 - 209, titled Why Believe the Judge? along with note from John which reads "This piece, please forward to Mr. Graves. I heartily approve of not commenting on commentary. Please tell him if he's read a little of (the) notes he's got the just, to stop. This essay is the only reason to mess with editors and delays and the like, Thank you, John.", undated (Box 786, Folder 1)
  - Spiral bound annotated typed manuscript titled More Notes on Cormac McCarthy's Blood Meridian and an Explication by John Emil Sepich, 1990 (Box 786, Folder 1)
  - Typed copy list of needs for the biographies and addenda along with disc containing various computer typed notes with folder titles "1993 Notes 1-2-06", "1993 Notes 1-16-06", "2005 Notes 4-16-06", "Illustrations with Names 4-16", 2006 (Box 786, Folder 1)
  - Typed letter addressed to Connie Todd & Steve Davis from Sepich referencing the research "word search/count" (results also attached) he completed on Blood Meridian, May 21, 2006 (Box 786, Folder 1)
  - Typed list "Omissions form the Blood Meridian concordance - generated for reconciliation" completed by Christopher Forbis and John Sepich, 1990 (Box 786, Folder 1)
  - Typed word search/count list "A brief look at word occurrence in Blood Meridian by Cormac McCarthy" completed by Christopher Forbis and John Sepich, 2006 (Box 786, Folder 1)
  - Numerous revised annotated drafts of sections of manuscript - revised sections include Sepich Mapping Glanton beginning with page 182 & Knitting the Winds beginning with page 173. Along with revisions is note from Sepich which reads "I'll sleep on what's at the bottom of this stack until I'm made to mess with it again John. N.B. These revisions began with Glanton (seemed the longest item) and then moved to the whole of "Knitting" prob. began just after the response to UTexas P.", June 26, 2006 - July 24, 2006 (Box 786, Folder 2)
  - Spiral bound annotated typed manuscript titled More Notes on Cormac McCarthy's Blood Meridian and an Explication by John Emil Sepich, 1990 (Box 786, Folder 3)
  - Spiral bound annotated copy of thesis by Sepich titled "Notes Toward and Explication of Cormac McCarthy's Blood Meridian, 1989 (Box 786, Folder 4)
  - Annotated typed manuscript, undated (Box 786, Folder 5)
  - Individual section of materials relating to University of Texas Press.
    Series Description
    Materials relating to The University of Texas Press. Sepich has written notes for each section in quotations marks, followed by a description of the contents.
    - "These are early contacts with U of Texas Press" contents include: typed letter addressed to Theresa May dated June 10, 2006, copy of index & table of contents page for Sepich's manuscript, and typed letter addressed to Theresa May dated June 11, 2006 (Box 786, Folder 6)
    - "These are draft and copy of "assent" of first letter to McCarthy (26 Oct. 88) and his response (8 May 89), this original is in the Southern Historical Collection at UNC-CH. I have no rights to his stuff, so it's view only. Mine? - do whatever. (I refuse to re-read it)" contents include: annotated draft of handwritten letter addressed Dear Mr. McCarthy along with copy of sent letter with revisions made. Photocopy of McCarthy's response to Sepich's letter is also attached., 1988-1989 (Box 786, Folder 6)
    - "These are my copies of Ralph Smith letters. The originals are in the Southern Historical Collection, UNC-CH. He was kind to me, and a Texan, as I give them to you for your kindnesses. His estate has all rights, so these are view only." contents include: photocopies of correspondence from/to Smith & Sepich, undated (Box 786, Folder 6)
    - "Communication with Bellamine was odd (prob. to account for the early blank pages and left had T of C), but they'd not done a book before, and I did the best I could. These are what are gathered as scraps form those 3 weeks." contents include: various handwritten and typed notes along with page proofs on Notes on Blood Meridian, photocopy of article titled "La saignee vers l'Ouest" dated 11-19-92, photocopy of article titled "Best unknown major writer' seeks and receives privacy in El Paso" dated 4/26/92 referencing McCarthy, photocopy of map - Southwest region (Box 786, Folder 6)
    - "This is an 'I met McCarthy' piece I'd gotten from Jake Mills in '88 or early '89 - from a friend of his, as I remember. No idea about my Ritten house note. I have no rights, so it's view only, and I send it only as I have no idea if anyone else has collected it. If they have (by way of the author) then this is best discarded. Early first - person will be the best there is in the long run, I think. I plan to refuse to revise "conversations." contents include: photocopies of photographs and short typed manuscript recounted by Larry Johnson, who used present tense and tried to relate the events in chronological order, titled "Larry Johnson and Robert Wegner Meet Cormac McCarthy" dated May 23, 1989 (Box 786, Folder 6)
  - Binder containing numerous photocopies of correspondence, mostly addressed to McCarthy referencing Notes on Blood Meridian, May - September 2003 (Box 786, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous materials: correspondence, various notes, compact disc titled by donor as "Notes 1993 ver.", photocopies of newspaper articles, photocopy of cover page of John H. Wallace's The Horse of America, photocopy of two early McCarthy stories Wake for Susan & A Drowning Incident, photocopy of typed short manuscript titled "Conversations With McCarthy" by Sepich, photocopy of article titled "The Scalp Business on the Border, 1837-1850" by Ray Brandes and Ralph A. Smith, and photocopies of various letters from/to Edwin T. Arnold III & McCarthy dates range 1979 - 1980 (Box 786, Folder 8)
  - Photocopy of Appendix C from Daniel Young, Jr.'s dissertation titled Blood Meridian and History, along with a February 20, 1992 handwritten letter addressed Dear John from Dianne Luce (Box 786, Folder 9)
  - Photocopies of the dispositions of the Yuma ferry massacre from the Arizona Historical Society, undated (Box 786, Folder 9)
  - Clean manuscript pages for Notes on Blood Meridian with revisions already made from earlier notes, undated (Box 786, Folder 9)
  - Typed pages of random "thoughts" developed by Sepich referencing Notes on Blood Meridian, circa Fall 1993 (Box 786, Folder 9)
  - Assorted materials: correspondence between Sepich and Shelby Foote, typed list of place of names in Blood Meridian along with page citations, photocopy of On Going Over my Notes by Sepich copyright dated 1993, handwritten thoughts & suggestions for Blood Meridian on photocopy of map - Southwest region, photocopies of tear sheets from American Heritage dated October 1992 referencing McCarthy's Blood Meridian, and correspondence between Phillippe Garnier & Sepich dated 1992 (Box 786, Folder 10)
- Accession 2007-014
  Notes and correspondence relating to Cormac McCarthy's Blood Meridian.
  - List of names in Blood Meridian, with page citations, undated (Box 783, Folder 5)
  - Three photocopied pages titled "Conversations with Bill McCarthy," with handwritten notes in the margin, November 12-13, 1992 (Box 783, Folder 5)
  - Photocopies of correspondence between John Sepich and Shelby Foote, mainly about Blood Meridian, 1991-1992 (Box 783, Folder 5)
- Accession 2008-005
  Material from the first Cormac McCarthy Conference held at Bellarmine College, Louisville, Kentucky, 1993. Also includes a poem and essay by Sepich.
  - "Cormac McCarthy: The First Conference" posters, circa 1993
    - Tan poster (11" x 17") stamped in red ink "Student Affairs" for the conference held at Bellarmine College campus in Louisville Kentucky, October 15-17, 1993 (Box 1003)
    - Two 11" x 17" posters, glossy prints, one is inscribed to John and signed (unknown), undated (Box 1003)
  - Registration materials and schedules for the "Cormac McCarthy: The First Conference", circa 1993 (Box 1003)
  - Poem titled "Dawn" signed by John Sepich, 1973 (Box 1003)
  - Essay, "The Judge's Two Hats: Or, the Palidrome in Cormac McCarthy's Blood Meridan with afterword by John Sepich, March 2007 (Box 1003)
  - Color photo from the "Cormac McCarthy Brain Trust" (described as such in letter to Connie Todd) taken at the conference in 1993 showing "LTR: Rick Wallach, Chip Arnold, Dianne Luce-Cox and me (John Sepich)" (Box 1003)
- Accession 2008-043
  Two early copies of Sepich's "Notes on Blood Meridian."
  - Two copies, one with a blue cover and one with a green cover, of Sepich's "Notes on 'Blood Meridan." Both signed by author. Both are spiral bound and in fair condition, undated (Box 1002, Folder 11)
- Accession 2009-072
  Correspondence between Sepich and Connie Todd, Wes Morgan, and Peter Josyph.
  - Letter to Wittliff Collections Director, Connie Todd, from John Sepich in reference to material, 2009 (Box 1230, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence from Wes Morgan to Chris Forbis in reference to Cormac McCarthy's "Suttree", undated (Box 1230, Folder 10)
  - Letter to John Sepich from Peter Josyph, includes two 8" x 10" black and white photographs taken by Josyph of Jim Long and Paulo Faria; also includes letter to Sepich from Faria, undated (Box 1230, Folder 10)
- Accession 2010-012
  Correspondence from Sepich to Connie Todd and from Cormac McCarthy to Sepich. Includes appraisal by John Payne. Also included are essays by Sepich.
  - Correspondence between Sepich and Connie Todd, circa 2010 (Box 1250, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence between Sepich and Cormac McCarthy; one piece of correspondence from McCarthy to Sepich has been appraised by John Payne [note from Payne included with material], undated (Box 1250, Folder 14)
  - Typed manuscripts "Other People's Pets" and "Transfer Level Composition" by Sepich, undated (Box 1250, Folder 14)
  - Typed manuscript of "Conversations with McCarthy", undated (Box 1250, Folder 15)
  - Printout of the Powerpoint "The Route and Roots of The Road" by Wesley Morgan from the University of Tennessee, undated (Box 1250, Folder 15)
  - CD-R with the Wesley Morgan material related to "The Route and Roots of The Road" by Wesley Morgan from the University of Tennessee, undated (Box 1250, Folder 15)
- Accession 2010-076
  Correspondence between Sepich and Portuguese writer Paulo Faria who translated several of Cormac McCarthy's works into Portuguese. Also included is one print of McCarthy by artist Palmer Murphy.
  - Correspondence between Sepich and Cormac McCarthy's Portuguese translator, Paulo Faria, undated (Box 1255, Folder 11)
  - Notes from Paulo Faria's visit to the collection to research McCarthy's material, "First Day at the Archives", undated (Box 1255, Folder 11)
  - One art print (11" x 17") of ink drawing "Cormac Visits Oprah," by Palmer Murphy, 2007 (Box 1003)
- Accession 2010-116
  Sepich correspondence and writings.
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1255)
  - Sepich thesis, "Notes Toward an Explication of Cormac McCarthy's Blood Meridan", undated (Box 1255)
- Accession 2014-156
  Materials relating to foreign language translations of McCarthy's work.
  - Czech literary journal, Host, September McCarthy issue. Include original English questions and responses on McCarthy's work translated in the journal, undated (Box 1883, Folder 10)
  - Printouts of statistics on countries seeking information on McCarthy's novels, and a letter of explanation from Sepich, undated (Box 1883, Folder 10)